Applications of machine learning and AI have proliferated at astounding speeds
due to the maturing of a variety of use cases, as well as ever-increasing amount
of data and network connectivity.
AI so far for the most part has used a centralized model where large amounts of
data are aggregated and processed,
and as a result has given rise to various business models
where “data monopolies” are created with strengthening network effects, a
phenomenon often seen in the consumer internet space.
Applications are also having to upgrade their data infrastructure and datacenters for
rapidly growing amounts of structured and unstructured data.
However, the trend of evolving data and AI-enabled capabilities have come to crossroads
with increasing issues regarding user data privacy, enterprise data privacy, as well as
tightening data regulations across various jurisdictions across the world.
As a result, an increasing number of enterprises and individuals are
wary to use and engage with applications and interaction touchpoints
where data privacy is unclear or in doubt,  creating new bottlenecks for various
data-intensive  AI use cases.
What’s fascinating however, is that these also come at the same time as steadily
rising number of IoT and smart devices,
as well as devices having increasingly powerful computational capacity,
as well as a growing of trend of applications looking to “decentralize” computation, increase
performance, and improve data sovereignty by leveraging edge computing technology.
All of these factors are fueling a rise in a new machine learning paradigm – what
we refer to as Federated Learning.
Federated Learning is a newer approach to AI where collaborative AI from data of various
users and participants can occur without having to sacrifice data privacy
at the same time of potentially better safeguarding data security.
Federated Learning decentralizes the process by training models across local computing nodes or devices
instead of aggregating data and training centrally, which is the prevalent method currently.
This also reduces the computational burden of the original single-party machine learning
approach by leveraging computation resources of localized devices and edge computing.
Actual implementation of federated learning solutions often touches upon a number of technologies
at the intersection machine learning, deep learning, blockchain, IoT and edge computing.
Federated Learning is already being used and tested, sometimes at large scale across various
industries including finance, healthcare, smart vehicles, consumer applications, and manufacturing.
It is however still in its relative infancy in terms of technology and adoption maturity.
The implementation of the technology, best-practices, nuances, and know-hows are relatively
obscure for various enterprises and organizations and often are not well documented.
Federated Learning Consortium, or FLC, is a global non-profit organization whose goals are to
advance the understanding and real world use-cases of federated learning
as well as related privacy-preserving technologies such as multi-party computation, in a collaborative manner
in which research, technology solutions, system integration know-how, and practical
case studies are synergized, as well as through discussion and project collaboration.